Guide to the
Brown University Library
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to [unknown], 1858 July 7; 2 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 66)
  Concerns plans for Jessie White Mario to travel to the United States in order to give lectures and generate American support for the Italian revolutionary effort. Both Mazzini and the letter's receipient support Jessie Mario White's trip, believing that she is adequately qualified to assume such an endeavor.
  Ms 629
  Mario, Jessie White, 1832-1906
- The death of Mazzini, 1961; 1 page; Carter, David G., 1921- (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 66-67, tucked between pages)
  Newspaper clipping of an article by David G. Carter, director of the Museum of Art of the Rhode Island School of Design about Silvestro Lega's painting of Mazzini on his deathbed, held by RISD. The article is published on the centenary of Italy's unification. Carter discusses Mazzini's life and Lega's activities as a member of the maccihaioli artistic group. Contains an image of the painting. A handwritten [librarian's] note at the top of the page indicates that the clipping was inserted into the album on May 29, 1961.
  Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872; Lega, Silvestro, 1826-1895
- Mazzini. Last Days of the Agitator—His Illness and Death–The Funeral Honors, 1872 March 14; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 67)
  Newspaper article written on the occasion of Giuseppe Mazzini's death, recounting his final days of hiding in Pisa under the fake name of "Dr. Brown", his illness, and his funeral. Attention is given to the funerary wreath that was displayed on his coffin bearing the inscription, "The Americans to Mazzini."
- Anonymous report, circa 1849; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 67)
  Handwritten, untitled report on military and political events in France. Document is divided into seven sections, apparently reporting on seven different developments. One section reports on a M. d'André, former cabinet head of the ex-minister of foreign affairs, being newly appointed ambassador to Dresden in Saxony to replace M. Reinhardt, the newly appointed envoy to the Swiss: this happened in July 1849. Considerable attention is also given to the affairs of Pierre-Joseph Proudhon, the French politician and anarchist who in 1849 was arrested for offending President Louis-Napoléon Bonaparte.
  Proudhon, P.-J. (Pierre-Joseph), 1809-1865
- [illegible] to "My dear sir"London, England, 1858 July 7; 3 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 68)
  Thanks the addressee for the advice he has given to be passed on to Jessie Mario White. Goes on to recount the situation of a terminally ill and dying friend who would like to return to Austria to die on native soil. Because of the slow speed of the Austrian consolate, the letter-writer requests that an American passport be granted to his friend to be able to make the journey home. Letter contains label, "Private and confidential."
  Ms 630
- Kossuth in old age, circa 1894 March; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 68)
  Newspaper clipping of an article written during the dying days of the Hungarian patriot Lajos Kossuth. Kossuth is quoted speaking about the future of the Austrian empire, republicanism in Europe, and America in the coming twentieth century. Article has been ripped in three pieces.
  Kossuth, Lajos, 1802-1894
- A new nation, 1889; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 68)
  Newspaper clipping of an article written in anticipation of Lajos (here anglicized to "Louis") Kossuth's loss of Hungarian citizenship after having lived abroad for forty years. As of January 1, 1890, Kossuth will no longer be a Hungarian citizen, but he refuses to adopt Italian citizenship even after having lived in Italy for many years, so he will become a one-man "Republic of Kossuth." Through a satirical reflection on the future of the "Kossuth State," the article comments upon nationality and statehood. Article has been ripped in two pieces.
- Kossuth and his sister, 1890 October; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 68)
  Newspaper clipping containing the text of a letter written to "a lady of Plainfield, N.J." by Louise Kossuth Ruttkay, sister to the Hungarian patriot Lajos Kossuth. The letter recounts Kossuth Ruttkay's recent visit to Hungary.
  Kossuth, Lajos, 1802-1894; Ruttkay, Louise Kossuth
- Kossuth dying London, England, 1894 March 20; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 68-69, bound between pages)
  Newspaper clipping from an article published in the London Evening Standard announcing that the Hungarian patriot Lajos Kossuth is dying. Contains an account of Kossuth's career.
- Magyar revolution believed to be near New York, NY, 2108; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 68-69, tucked between pages)
  Newspaper clipping from a New York Times article reporting on revolutionary tensions in Hungary. Connections drawn between contemporary era and the revolutionary activities of 1848-49. Includes four images: portraits of Lajos (anglicized "Louis") Kossuth and his son Ferencz (anglicized "Francis") Kossuth, a view entitled "The Parliament Bldg. Budapest", and a scene of men gathered with swords, entitled "Declaiming a Revolutionary Poem March 15th 1848."
  Kossuth, Lajos, 1802-1894; Kossuth, Ferencz Lajos Àkos, 1841-1914
- Rusconi, Carlo to Ministro degli affari esteri del regno di Napoli Rome, Italy, 1849 February 26; 1 page; Rusconi, Carlo, 1812-1889 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 69)
  Typewritten letter protesting the accumulation of Neapolitan troops on the border of the Roman Republic and the entrance of one hundred Neapolitan soldiers on republican lands. The letter is sent to the Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Kindgom of Naples in the hope that war can be prevented. Possibly a transcript of the original.
- [illegible] to [unknown], 1849 June 24; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 70)
  Text of letter reads: "My dear Sir, Pray come here as soon as possible to sign the remonstrance which must go to the camp immediately. In haste yours truly [illegible]."
  Ms 633
- [unknown] to [unknown]Rome, Italy, 1847 February 8; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 70-71, bound between pages)
  Regards a social invitaton that would have involved Caroline Matilda Clements Brown and a Monsieur Polk.
  Ms 634
  Brown, Caroline Matilda Clements
- Santangelo, Gen. [illegible first name] to Brown, Nicholas Rome, Italy, 1849 April 3; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 71)
  Italian revolutionary general asks for help in finding safe lodgings while he awaits to embark at the port of Civitavecchia, fearing that he may in the meantime be captured by Napoleone's forces, hanged without mercy, or "cut to pieces." Santangelo further asks that Brown forward the enclosed letter under the American consular seal to "my poor little Mary" to calm her fears about his fate. Hopes for a decisive answer from Brown.
  Ms 635
  Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859
- Receipt for appartment and linen Rome, Italy, 1848 April 17; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 72)
  Handwritten receipt for payment made by Nicholas Brown to rent an appartment in Rome. Additional money was also paid for linen. Signature on receipt is illegible.
  Ms 636
- Muti, Gio. Paolo, Vice Presidente della Commisione Provvisoria municipale di Roma to Brown, Nicholas Rome, Italy, 1849 April 7; 1 page; Muni, Gio. Paolo (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 72-73, bound between pages)
  Official invitation from the Vice President of the Temporary Municipal Commission of Rome to attend illumination of the dome of St. Peter's Basilica in celebration of Easter.
  Ms 637
- Agli associati dell'alba Florence, Italy, 1849 April; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 73)
  Flyer announcing the temporary suspension of the publication Alba in order to avoid the attacks of which it had repeatedly become the target.
- Lowe, Alfred to Brown, Nicholas Civitavecchia, Italy, 1849 April 24; 1 page; Lowe, Alfred (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 74-75, bound between pages)
  Informs Brown of the landing of French General Oudinot and his troops to begin a "peaceful occupation" of Civita Vecchia on the part of the French government. Includes details about the numbers of troops. States that a copy of Oudinot's declaration to the "Preside" of the city is included. Address on outside of letter is accompanied by a sketch, possibly illustrating a weapon.
  Ms 638
  Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859; Oudinot, Nicolas-Charles, duc de Reggio, 1767-1847
- Lowe, Alfred to Brown, Nicholas Civitavecchia, Italy, 1849 April 25; 2 page; Lowe, Alfred (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 76-77, bound between pages)
  Informs Brown of the progress since his letter of the previous day of French efforts to occupy the city of Civitavecchia. Observes that the flags of both France and the Roman Republic are being flown; includes details about the quartering of soldiers; and notes that while a few individuals proposed resisting French entry, those proposals were overruled.
  Ms 638a
- Triumvirato della Repubblica Romana to Brown, Nicholas, Cittadino degli stati uniti d'america Rome, Italy, 1849 May 3; 2 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872; Saffi, Aurelio, 1819-1890; Armellini, Carlo, 1777-1863 (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 78-79, bound between pages)
  Regards the request made by Brown that the government of the Roman Republic allow an American citizen by the name of Benjamin and his wife to travel to the town of Albano. Although the Triumvirate's high esteem for the nation of the United States causes them to entertain the consul's request, the letter observes what a poor political move it is for an American citizen to leave the territory of the Roman Republic and venture towards Albano just as the Neapolitans are arriving there. Does Benjamin have greater faith in the Republic's enemies, they ask, than in the Republic? The Triumvirate was the government briefly composed of Giuseppe Mazzini, Aurelio Saffi, and Carlo Armellini.
  Ms 639
- Lowe, Alfred to Brown, Nicholas Civitavecchia, Italy, 1849 May 4; 2 pages; Lowe, Alfred (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 80-81, bound between pages)
  Apologizes for not having continued his daily updates of the arrival of French troops in Civitavecchia after his earlier letters of April 24 and April 25 (see bdr710161 and bdr710162), citing lack of developments and the suspension of the post for Rome as causes for the interruption. Remarks the ongoing arrival of French ships of war and notes that, since some troops are arriving in Civitavecchia and marching to Rome while others are marching to Civitavecchia from the direction of Rome, "the intentions of the French are not to be known." Reports rumors about the arrival in Civitavecchia of the Prince Del Carretto in disguise. A postscript to the letter reports upon the passage in nearby waters of the American ship "Princeton," said to be carrying diplomats from Florence to meet the Grand Duke of Tuscany at Gaeta.
  Ms 640
- Rusconi, Carlo, Ministro degli affari esteri to Brown, Nicholas, Agente consolare degli stati uniti Rome, Italy, 1849 May 8; 1 page; Rusconi, Carlo, 1812-1889 (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 82-83, bound between pages)
  Rusconi sends Brown a copy of one of his notes written to the Catholic Authorities, requesting that he examine it with the attention it requires.
  Ms 641
- Lowe, Alfred to Brown, Nicholas Civitavecchia, Italy, 1849 May 15; 1 page; Lowe, Alfred (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 84-85, bound between pages)
  Continues series of letters providing Brown updates on the French occupation of Civitavecchia. Includes names of recently-landed ships with numbers of troops and weapons. Announces arrival of Ferdinand de Lesseps (French envoy with the mission to "examine thoroughly into the real state of things, and to act accordingly") and the chargeé d'affaires of the Roman Republic at Paris: both are heading towards Rome. See previous letters: bdr710161, bdr710162, and bdr710167.
  Ms 642
  Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859; Lesseps, Ferdinand de, 1805-1894
- Lowe, Alfred to Brown, Nicholas Civitavecchia, Italy, 1849 May 22; 2 page; Lowe, Alfred (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 86-87, bound between pages)
  Continues series of letters providing Brown updates on the French occupation of Civitavecchia. Lowe thanks Brown for his most recent letter, before going on to note the "constant arrival of French troops" and artillery. Also remarks the departures of steamboats from Civitavecchia, including the monthly schedule of French mail boats and steamboats heading towards Leghorn. See previous letters: bdr710161, bdr710162, bdr710167, and bdr710172. Address page of letter also contains a handwritten list that includes napkins, drawers, and night gowns, in addition to other items.
  Ms 643
- Reppublica Romana, Ministri del commercio e lavori pubblici to Brown, Nicholas Rome, Italy, 1849 May 25; 1 page; Repubblica Romana, Ministeri del Commercio e Lavori Pubblici (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 88)
  Gives permission for Brown and a guest to visit the Vatican Library, provided that all regulations are followed.
  Ms 644
- de Gerando, E. M., Chancellerie, Chargé des Affaires, Ambassade de France á Rome to Brown, Nicholas Rome, Italy, 1849 June 2; 1 page; de Gerando, E. M.; Ambassade de France a Rome (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 89)
  A travel pass issued by the French embassy in Rome to allow Brown to travel to Civitavecchia, accompanied by his wife, two children, and Doctor Pertrius, his doctor, in his own car and with his horses. He is to proceed to the consulate general upon his arrival there.
  Ms 645
- Lowe, Alfred to Brown, Nicholas Civitavecchia, Italy, 1849 June 11; 2 pages; Lowe, Alfred (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 90)
  Continues series of letters providing Brown updates on the French occupation of Civitavecchia. Lowe here reports the arrival of two diplomats (Henri-Godefroi-Bernard-Alphonse, prince de La Tour d'Auvergne and a member of the Corcelle family) on a mission of the government of the French Republic: although he does not know what their instructions may be, they have proceeded directly to the troops' encampment. Also reports rumors that the French are preparing a forced entry [into Rome?] the next day. See previous letters: bdr710161, bdr710162, bdr710167, bdr710172, and bdr710174. A note added next to the letter's external address reports that the letter was received on June 15 at 10am.
  Ms 646
  Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859; De La Tour d'Auvergne, Henri-Godefroi-Bernard-Alphonse
- Envelopes, 4 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 90-91, tucked between pages)
  Three envelopes of mail that had been sent to Brown in Rome. One is addressed "All'onorevole cittadino console degli stati uniti d'america" and is blank on the inside. A second is addressed to "Brown Esq Consul of the United States" and contains the following note on the inside: "With M. Mazzini's best compliments. June 7." A final envelope, which seems to have been sent from Geneva, Switzerland, is addressed to Brown using his full formal title in Italian; arithmetic calculations have been made in the top corner of the envelope.
  Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872
- Letter to Brown, Nicholas signed by 6 Italian consuls/charge d'affaires including Corboli, Curzio and Galiotti, F.Rome, Italy, 1849 June 24; 2 pages; Galiotti, F.; Corboli, Curzio (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 92)
  Regards French projectile attacks on the city of Rome, which have been ongoing for twenty-two days, have damaged even the city's most well-known monuments, and have victimized elderly people, women, and children. After describing the dire situation to Brown, the six signees of this letter present Brown the hope that, as the representative of a great and civil nation and in the interest of humanitarianism, he will come to their aid and help prevent the outbreak of war.
  Ms 647
- Almte to Brown, Nicholas, 1849 June 25; 2 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 93)
  Tells Brown that he has not received the circular that the government of Rome has sent to the other consuls and chargés d'affaires, since the government does not consider him "a representative in matters diplomatic or consular." Furthermore, Almte has recently had a dispute with French troops about the passage of some of his countrymen: for this reason he cannot sign onto any communication with Oudinot.
  Ms 648
- Lowe, Alfred to Brown, Nicholas Civitavecchia, Italy, 1849 June 26; 1 page; Lowe, Alfred (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 94-95, bound between pages)
  Continues series of letters providing Brown updates on the French occupation of Civitavecchia. Because the French have stopped all communication between Civitavecchia and Rome, Lowe must update Brown not in writing, but rather through Alex Lemmi, Brown's messenger from Paris. See previous letters: bdr710161, bdr710162, bdr710167, bdr710172, bdr710174, and bdr710178.
  Ms 649
  Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859; Lemmi, Alex
- Roselli, Pietro, Generale in Capo del Comando generale dell'armata della Repubblica romana to Il senatore di Roma Rome, Italy, 1849 July 4; 1 page; Roselli, Pietro; Repubblica Romana, Comando Generale Dell'Armata (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 96)
  Requests that passports be obtained from the English or American consuls to allow military personnel who would be in danger if there were to return to their homes to instead travel to other places where they might find safety.
  Ms 650
- Carli, Carlo to Brown, Nicholas Comacchio, Italy, 1849 August 3; 2 pages; Bonafede, Carli conte Carlo; Consulate of the United States of America in Comacchio (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 98)
  Reports the defeat of boats carrying Garibaldi and his men by the Austrian fleet in the waters off the port of Goro. According to Carli, Garibaldi is said to have escaped with his wife, staff, and some soldiers to land between the ports of Magnavacca and Volano: many of these, including Garibaldi and his wife, are said to have set off across the territory disguised as country peasants. Among Garibaldi's disembarked soldiers were Father Ugo Bassi (a Bolognese priest) and a Captain Ringhini, who headed towards Comacchio only to be arrested for not carrying passports: they are now in jail in Comacchio. Carli promises to update Brown as further information becomes available to him.
  Ms 651
  Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859; Garibaldi, Giuseppe, 1807-1882; Bassi, Ugo, 1801-1849
- Latimer, H.K. to Brown, Nicholas Bay of Spezzia, Italy, 1849 November 16; 2 pages; Latimer, H. K. (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 100)
  Regards the case of Joseph Eismenger, an adolescent Hungarian boy on board Latimer's U.S. Frigate Cumberland. Latimer recounts what he has learned of Joseph: that during the 1848 Hungarian revolution he joined the army with his father—Anton Eismenger—and brother; that his father and brother were killed as prisoners of war; that Joseph escaped to Switzerland and then Italy, where he joined Latimer's ship. Latimer asks Brown to find information about Joseph's uncle, Ferdinand Eismenger, a Hungarian general who is said to have survived and escaped to Rome, or any other surviving relations of the boy, such as possibly an aunt who now lives in a convent in Rome.
  Ms 652
  Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859; Eismenger, Anton; Eismenger, Ferdinand; Eismenger, Joseph
- Deposizione di Ceccarini, Gaetano Rome, Italy, 1849 June 6; 6 pages; Ceccarini, Gaetano; Gagiotti, Giacomo (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 103)
  Notarized deposition issued by the Roman Republic testifying to brutalities committed by French soldiers invading Rome. The deponent and several other men fighting to defend the Roman Republic were supposedly thrown out of windows by the French, causing the death of at least two. Accompanied by official English translation of deposition. Name of notary: Giacomo Gagiotti.
  Ms 653, Ms 654
- Nicholas Brown's personal congratulations on creation of Roman Republic Rome, Italy, 1849 February; 2 pages; Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 104)
  Draft, with edits added in pencil between penned lines, of a communication prepared by Nicholas Brown to congratulate the leaders of the Roman Republic on the establishment of a democratically-elected government. Although Brown is not authorized to make any proclamation on behalf of the American government, he wishes to express his "personal satisfaction at this memorable event." Brown goes on to note that it has previously always been a "cardinal principle" of the American government "to acknowledge as supreme any government which a people may choose to institute," since a people have "the fundamental right of subverting or remodelling old forms of rule, or establishing a new order of things." The communication concludes by insisting that because of Americans' love of liberty, the establishment of the Roman Republic will be celebrated across America long before diplomats have time to speak officially on the issue. Both pages of the document contain handwritten pencil notes on the reverse: one reads, "To Roman Govt"; the other notes that "a copy of this was sent in my name to Mr. Buchanan, Sec of State."
  Ms 655
  Buchanan, James, 1791-1868
- Brown, Nicholas to Rusconi, Carlo Rome, Italy, 1849 February 18; 2 pages; Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 105)
  Assures Rusconi, the foreign affairs minister of the Roman Republic, that the government of the United States will recognize the Roman Republic at the nearest opportune moment. Brown goes on to express his enthusiasm for the Roman Republic, praising in particular the calm that its government has been able to maintain despite turbulent circumstances and speaking of a new "modern Rome" that follows in the legacy of the great men of its storied past. Contains handwritten edits, some in English.
  Ms 656
  Rusconi, Carlo, 1812-1889
- Brown, Nicholas to Monsieur Ambassadeur Rome, Italy, 1849; 4 pages; Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 106)
  Draft of a letter regarding the petition signed by Brown and other consuls in Rome and sent to General Charles Oudinot to end the bombardment of the city by French troops. Brown references newspaper coverage of the affair, including a letter to Oudinot published by Karl von Kolb, Consul of Württemburg. Brown protests the ambassador's response to the bombardment and goes on to cite his reasons for signing the petition, including the suffering of innocent victims and the destruction of public property.
  Ms 657
  Oudinot, Nicolas-Charles, duc de Reggio, 1767-1847; von Kolb, Karl
- Some drunken French soldiers at the American consulate Rome, Italy, 1849; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 107)
  Description of an occurence involving "some drunken French soldiers" outside the house of the American consul in Rome. After the French soldiers were prevented from forcing their way into the house in pursuit of individuals whom they perceived to be laughing at them, they arrested several Roman soldiers. The American consul Nicholas Brown informed the French General Oudinot of the situation, who immediately ordered the release of the seized men: an apology was made.
  Ms 658
  Oudinot, Nicolas-Charles, duc de Reggio, 1767-1847; Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859
- Brown, Nicholas to Monsieur l' Ambassadeur de Corcelles Geneva, Switzerland, 1849 August 18; 3 pages; Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 108)
  Draft of a letter regarding the petition signed by Brown and other consuls in Rome and sent to General Charles Oudinot to end the bombardment of the city by French troops. Brown references newspaper coverage of the affair, including a letter to Oudinot published by Karl von Kolb, Consul of Württemburg. Brown protests the ambassador's response to the bombardment and goes on to cite his reasons for signing the petition, including the suffering of innocent victims and the destruction of public property. See also: bdr710158.
  Ms 659
- Draft of Brown, Nicholas to Rusconi, Carlo Rome, Italy, 1849 February 18; 2 pages; Brown, Nicholas, 1792-1859 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 109)